<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of the King stated, from the very beginning of the warre to this present day, in relation I. To the two Houses. II. To the Army. III. To the Scots. IV. To the subjects of England in generall. In justification &amp; commiseration of his Majesty in this his distressed condition; and for the satisfaction of the whole kingdom. / By Basilius Anonymus.</title>
            <author>Basilius Anonymus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1099</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E416_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204479</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863969</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863969</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116187</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78251)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116187)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E416[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of the King stated, from the very beginning of the warre to this present day, in relation I. To the two Houses. II. To the Army. III. To the Scots. IV. To the subjects of England in generall. In justification &amp; commiseration of his Majesty in this his distressed condition; and for the satisfaction of the whole kingdom. / By Basilius Anonymus.</title>
                  <author>Basilius Anonymus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeere 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Basilius Anonymus is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The words "I. To the two Houses. .. generall." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116187:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116187:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The CASE of THE KING STATED, From the very beginning of the Warre to this preſent day, In relation I. To the <hi>two Houſes.</hi> II. To the <hi>Army.</hi> III. To the <hi>Scots.</hi> IV. To the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> in generall. In juſtification &amp; commiſeration of His <hi>Majeſty</hi> in this his diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed condition; and for the ſatisfaction of the whole Kingdom. By BASILIUS ANONYMUS.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>—Nemo me impunè laceſsit.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>O fooliſh <hi>Galatians,</hi> who hath bewitched you?
<bibl>
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of the British royal family</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               </head>
               <p>C. R.</p>
               <p>HONI SOIT QVI MAY Y PENSE</p>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed in the Yeere 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116187:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>King's</hi> moſt excellent Majeſty.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis poore Pamphlet I intended at firſt ſhould have kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed your <hi>Royall</hi> hands at <hi>Hampton</hi>-Court, not that I conceived it a <hi>Preſent</hi> worthy the acceptance of a King, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I preſumed, that <hi>Loyalty</hi> being a precious <hi>Jewell</hi> in this age, could not be unwelcome, though preſented from the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and the moſt unworthy of your Subjects.</p>
            <p>Some perſwaſions of your true <hi>Friends</hi> firſt put me upon the <hi>Enterpriſe,</hi> and urged to me a neceſsity, that it ſhould be done out of hand, that all your <hi>loyall Subjects</hi> might be informed in what a <hi>ſad condition</hi> you lay, and how miſerably you have been abuſed from time to time: ſo that it being the Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of but a day and a night (a little more time than <hi>Nature</hi> takes to the making of a <hi>Muſhrome,</hi>) nothing can be expected in it but <hi>plaine Truth</hi> hudled together without any artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>method</hi> or <hi>dreſſing.</hi> And yet I hope it will find your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> out in this your happy retirement; wherein if it ſpeake but any <hi>tolerable</hi> ſence to entertain your <hi>Majeſty</hi> for an houre, and ſuch as may take <hi>Impreſſion</hi> upon the hearts of your <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> then (though done in haſt) it is well done.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116187:2"/>
            <head>I. The <hi>Caſe</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> in relation to the two <hi>Houſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF we looke upon the ancient <hi>Majeſty</hi> of the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> for which this our native <hi>Countrey</hi> hath been held in as vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable an eſteem, as any <hi>Kingdom</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> whatſoever, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the preſent deſpicable condition of our now <hi>dread Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,</hi> into what an <hi>Abyſſe</hi> of miſery he is plunged by the <hi>Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of his own <hi>Subjects,</hi> (yet all under the ſpecious pretence of <hi>loyalty,</hi>) as there is no <hi>generous heart</hi> but muſt lament the Infamie which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes upon us, in the opinion of other <hi>Nations,</hi> ſo no <hi>Tongue</hi> or <hi>Pen</hi> will ever be able to <hi>fatham</hi> the depth of their <hi>vilany,</hi> no <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> equall their impiety, who firſt contributed to that <hi>curſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath permitted (for cauſes beſt knowne to his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable <hi>wiſdom</hi>) to render a <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>glorious</hi> Prince, a <hi>flouriſhing</hi> and <hi>obedient</hi> People, thus wretched and miſerable, by a moſt horrid <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is now more than five <hi>yeares,</hi> ſince the <hi>devouring ſword</hi> firſt ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged about the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> full ſeven yeares ſince this <hi>Parliament</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan; the whole <hi>Body</hi> whereof I cannot accuſe for the <hi>Authors</hi> of this <hi>unnaturall war,</hi> but (to ſpeake mildly and conſcionably) they were ſome few <hi>Members</hi> of it (whom it is not my buſines to name, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that to <hi>Hiſtory,</hi>) who <hi>firſt taught our Hands to war and our Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to fight.</hi> Yet he that will trace the deſigne of this <hi>warr</hi> to its <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall,</hi> ſhall finde it of an elder date than 7. yeares: For, all the <hi>ſeditious</hi> Carriages of the <hi>Puritan-Faction</hi> (ſo called) againſt the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church, in the dayes of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>Iames,</hi> and our <hi>Soveraigne</hi> that now is, were but as ſo many <hi>prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> to the work in hand, or ſo many <hi>throwes</hi> in <hi>Travaile,</hi> till the <hi>Faction</hi> was delivered of the <hi>Monſter,</hi> in the yeare 1641. which was then <hi>Chriſtned</hi> by the name of REFORMATION.</p>
            <p>And whereas in the <hi>Reignes</hi> of the two former <hi>Princes,</hi> this <hi>Faction</hi> was with great <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>policy,</hi> kept under Hatches, and ſo not arrived to that height of <hi>Impudence</hi> they afterward attained, their numbers being then not very conſiderable among the <hi>Nobility, Gentry,</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> of the Kingdom, and ſo they wanted men to back them both in the <hi>Senate</hi> and <hi>Pulpit;</hi> yet in proceſſe of time being very active and induſtrious, (as all <hi>Innovators</hi> muſt be) they drew <hi>Diſciples</hi> after them in all <hi>Counties</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> among all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and <hi>conditions</hi> of men: ſo that then their <hi>Reputation</hi> increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116187:3"/>with their <hi>number,</hi> and both being mightily advanced by an <hi>artificiall</hi> and <hi>counterfeit</hi> piety, they daily gathered advantage to cry downe the Government of the Church by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as <hi>Anti-Chriſtian,</hi> to make way for (as themſelves termed it) a <hi>glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation;</hi> This was made the <hi>Stalking horſe</hi> to the whole <hi>deſignes,</hi> and through this pretence they the rather prevailed upon the credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous people, by reaſon of the raſh and furious carriage of ſome of the <hi>Epiſcopall Clergy,</hi> which rendred their <hi>Adverſaries</hi> a daily occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to add <hi>fuell</hi> to the fire of <hi>zeale</hi> among the multitude, and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to entertaine any Change, though to their owne <hi>prejudice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which being quickly apprehended, and <hi>Counſells</hi> mutually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, by many of the <hi>Gentry,</hi> and a <hi>Lord</hi> or two (ſome of <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Fortunes,</hi> but all of <hi>ambitious</hi> minds) they judged then they had met with a fit occaſion to repaire and advance their <hi>Fortunes</hi> and their <hi>Friends,</hi> to the great <hi>Offices</hi> and <hi>Honors</hi> of the Kingdom, and ſo became Candidalets of this deſperate Faction. And knowing that this could never be effected but by ſurprizing the <hi>King's Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi> and the chiefe <hi>Officers</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> in a <hi>Parliamentary</hi> way, they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored tooth and naile (their expectations having been fruſtrated in former <hi>Parliaments</hi>) to make ſure of all in this <hi>Parliament:</hi> And this they mannaged moſt ſtoutly partly by canvaſing <hi>Elections</hi> for <hi>Creatures</hi> of their owne in the <hi>Counties</hi> abroad, partly by working upon the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> with <hi>religious pretences;</hi> and finally upon their owne Members with high <hi>promiſes;</hi> and that which gave the maine <hi>ſtroke</hi> of all was, their having the <hi>Scots</hi> ready at a <hi>Call</hi> (as the world well knew) upon all occaſions to back them.</p>
            <p>By which meanes having made their party <hi>paramount</hi> among the <hi>Laity,</hi> and knowing there was little hope but that all the learned Clergie of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> would ſtick firme to their owne <hi>Principles,</hi> as they attempted ſo they prevailed upon few of them; But well weighing the <hi>Proverb,</hi> That none is ſo bold as blind <hi>Bayard,</hi> and that, <hi>Ignorance</hi> is the mother of <hi>blind Obedience,</hi> they knew none ſo fit to worke to their owne ends, as the <hi>meaneſt</hi> and moſt <hi>illiterate</hi> of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> who were as ready to ſwallow the great <hi>Benefices,</hi> as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the great <hi>Offices</hi> of the Kingdome; and theſe they imployed both at <hi>Preſſe</hi> and <hi>Pulpit,</hi> to <hi>libell</hi> and <hi>raile</hi> downe the <hi>ancient</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived government both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now the <hi>Boutefeu's</hi> of the <hi>Faction</hi> being thus prepared, they proceeded to give <hi>fire,</hi> immediately diſ-mounted the chiefe <hi>Officers of State,</hi> and chaſed the <hi>Biſhops</hi> out of the <hi>Houſe of Lords,</hi> and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled all exorbitant <hi>Courts</hi> both <hi>ſpirituall</hi> and <hi>temporall;</hi> to all which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116187:3"/>His <hi>Majeſty</hi> gave his <hi>Royall Aſſent,</hi> as alſo for <hi>Trienniall Parliaments.</hi> To which ſpeciall <hi>Acts of Grace</hi> and <hi>Favor,</hi> he added alſo that higheſt of all, for the <hi>continuance</hi> of this <hi>Parliament</hi> at the diſcretion of our new <hi>Maſters;</hi> and what more could have been deſired, or granted? But they not yet ſatisfied, and the <hi>Court</hi> being crowded daily with unreaſonable demands, extorted by the <hi>Factious Party,</hi> from the <hi>Houſes,</hi> and as unreaſonable and audacious <hi>Tumults</hi> from the <hi>City,</hi> to the intolerable affront of the <hi>Royall Perſon,</hi> his Majeſty plainely ſaw the <hi>deſigne</hi> was next to chaſe himſelfe away, and experience tells us, it was a plot on purpoſe to lay a <hi>Foundation</hi> for <hi>war,</hi> by driving him to extremities, that themſelves might invade the <hi>Throne</hi> (as we ſee they have done,) and <hi>reigne like Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now having perfected the <hi>Plot</hi> thus farre, and attained the cheef of their deſires, which was His <hi>Majeſties</hi> abſence (whereupon they tooke occaſion of advantage in the opinion of the people, (as they ever have done upon the moſt <hi>neceſſitous</hi> and <hi>innocent</hi> of his Actions) to ſcandalize him for a <hi>Deſerter</hi> of his <hi>Parliament</hi>) it was conſulted next, to keep him away, and drive him to further <hi>extremities,</hi> and ſo they proſecuted him ſtill with ſuch imperious <hi>Meſſages</hi> and <hi>Demands,</hi> as became neither a <hi>wiſe</hi> nor <hi>loyall</hi> People to aske, nor an <hi>Engliſh</hi> King to grant, if he meant to be a King any longer, or they had meant really to have him returne back to <hi>London,</hi> with any hope of being uſed like a <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But on they proceeded, and the next worke was, to <hi>diſrobe</hi> him, of all the <hi>Enſignes</hi> of <hi>Royalty;</hi> and firſt, to raviſh the <hi>Crowne</hi> of its choiceſt <hi>Jewell,</hi> the <hi>Militia</hi> both by <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>Land;</hi> the very <hi>life</hi> and <hi>ſoule</hi> of a King <hi>quatenus</hi> King, and without which <hi>Monarchie</hi> is but a dead <hi>Carkaſe,</hi> a <hi>Scar-Crow,</hi> a mere <hi>Shadow.</hi> But becauſe it had been too groſſe to make ſo high and poſitive a <hi>Demand,</hi> without ſome gilded <hi>pretence,</hi> immediately wild <hi>Feares</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> were raiſed to amaze the people, concerning a <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Profane-Party,</hi> ready to joyne in Armes with the <hi>King,</hi> for the deſtruction of the <hi>Proteſtant Religiion,</hi> and inſlaving them to an <hi>Arbitrary Tyranny,</hi> whereupon they founded an <hi>invincible neceſsity</hi> lying upon the <hi>Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> to borrow the <hi>Militia</hi> for a certaine time out of the hands of the <hi>King,</hi> to ſecure the <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon the <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Integrity</hi> of His Majeſty, as if the Power of the Kingdome in his hands, had been like a ſword in the hands of a <hi>Mad-man,</hi> and no ſecurity to be expected, unleſſe it were put into their own; all which was cunningly repreſented to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> by way of <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> and <hi>Declaration</hi> from <hi>London,</hi> and all their fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116187:4"/>
               <hi>Allegations</hi> and <hi>pretences</hi> in them, as wiſely anſwerd, and the <hi>Rights</hi> of the <hi>Crown</hi> ſubſtantially defended by his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> in ſeverall Declarations likewiſe from <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be ſhort, this buſines of the <hi>Militia</hi> (which is his <hi>Majeſties</hi> chiefeſt and undoubted <hi>Right</hi>) was that which ſet this unnaturall warr on foot; for, th <hi>Houſes</hi> having ſeized it into their hands, and ſo his <hi>Majeſty</hi> being firſt aſſaulted, and knowing well whereto theſe <hi>unparalled'd</hi> Attempts tended, by the <hi>Series</hi> of their paſt <hi>proceedings,</hi> even to the diminution (if not utter deſtruction) of the <hi>Royall Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> which not to have defended and vindicated againſt manifeſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation,</hi> had been to betray his <hi>Poſterity,</hi> and the Majeſty of <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire;</hi> it muſt needs remaine cleare to all the <hi>World,</hi> that as his Majeſty was neceſſitated to a <hi>defenſive</hi> poſture, for the preſervation of his <hi>Crowne</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> (thus impiouſly <hi>invaded</hi>) ſo the <hi>two Houſes</hi> (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>factious</hi> party in them) were the firſt <hi>Authors</hi> and <hi>Actors</hi> of this miſerable <hi>Civill Warr,</hi> and of all thoſe miſchiefes thence ariſing to the <hi>Publique,</hi> in purſuance of their owne <hi>private ends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farr it was judged neceſſary to <hi>premiſe</hi> in juſtification of his Majeſties <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Innocencie,</hi> touching the ground of the <hi>Warr</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Him &amp; the <hi>two Houſes.</hi> Now as touching the <hi>Continuation</hi> of it, wee muſt add that likewiſe to their <hi>Accompt</hi> who were the firſt <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers:</hi> for <hi>Blowes</hi> being paſt on both ſides, and ſo the <hi>Warr</hi> well on foot, and they having taſted a while of the <hi>ſweets</hi> of <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded ſtill to proſecute it upon the ſame <hi>Principles</hi> that they began it, and kept of his <hi>Majeſty</hi> from all poſſibility of an <hi>Accomodation,</hi> by freſh ſupplies of <hi>Demands</hi> more <hi>Monſtrous</hi> and unreaſonable then the firſt. And of this ſtraine were the <hi>Nineteene Propoſitions</hi> preſented by Commiſſioners of both <hi>Houſes,</hi> to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> at <hi>Colebrooke,</hi> the <hi>Propoſitions</hi> of both <hi>Kingdomes</hi> preſented firſt at <hi>Oxford,</hi> a ſecond time at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> and now lately again at <hi>Hampton-court;</hi> to all which his <hi>Majeſty</hi> returned convincing <hi>Reaſons</hi> of his <hi>Deniall,</hi> they being ſuch as he could not <hi>Aſſent</hi> unto, without manifeſt <hi>Violation</hi> of his <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> by yeelding up the <hi>Regall Dignity,</hi> with the <hi>Revenues, Rights,</hi> and <hi>Indowments</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> (which he is ſworne to defend) and a wilfull condemnation of his owne moſt juſt <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and all thoſe that have adhered cloſeſt to him in the midſt of <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as <hi>Propoſitions</hi> have been made uſe of hitherto, onely to vex Him, and delude the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> with pretended <hi>Offers</hi> toward an <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation,</hi> the ſame hath been the <hi>Aime</hi> likewiſe in all their <hi>Meſſages</hi> and <hi>Treaties,</hi> but eſpecially that maine one at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> where it is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116187:4"/>a ſhame to conſider how farr his <hi>Majeſty</hi> condeſcended unto them, out of his indeered affection to his wearied and waſted <hi>Subjects,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the procuring of a firm and <hi>well grounded Peace,</hi> valuing the quiet &amp; comfort of his <hi>People,</hi> before many known and undoubted <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> of the <hi>Crown.</hi> But the <hi>Houſes</hi> having then for ſome years ingroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the greateſt places of <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Profit</hi> in their owne hands, had not made then full <hi>Markets</hi> at the price of the <hi>Peoples</hi> bloud, and therefore kept ſtill at ſuch a diſtance, that all his <hi>Majeſties</hi> endeavours for <hi>Agreement,</hi> were rendred fruitleſſe and unprofitable; ſo that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the ſweet <hi>Muſick</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> expected by that <hi>Treaty,</hi> the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> trembled again with freſh <hi>Alarms</hi> unto the <hi>warr,</hi> and all turned to confuſion.</p>
            <p>And in proceſſe of time, <hi>Divine Providence</hi> permitting his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Affaires</hi> to fall into a very <hi>low condition,</hi> by a continued hurry of <hi>Loſſes</hi> from that miraculous and fatall Battell of <hi>Naſeby</hi> to a totall disbanding in the <hi>Weſt;</hi> and when none had eſcaped the fury of the <hi>Enemie,</hi> but a few ſcattered languiſhing <hi>Gariſons</hi> in the heart of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> his <hi>Majeſty</hi> was forced to make many an <hi>Overture</hi> for a <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall Treaty;</hi> for the better expediting whereof, he offered himſelfe (upon ſecurity given) to come &amp; <hi>Treat</hi> with them at <hi>Weſtminſter:</hi> But the <hi>deafe Adders ſtopped their eares, and would not hearken to the voice of the Charmer charmed he never ſo wiſely;</hi> though he promiſed to give and take all the <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> that could be required by <hi>Reaſonable</hi> and <hi>Conſcientious</hi> men. And ſo his <hi>Majeſty</hi> having failed of his <hi>laſt Refuge,</hi> a <hi>Perſonall Treaty,</hi> he was not long after beſeiged in <hi>Oxford</hi> by Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and driven to ſuch extremity, that he was glad to quit the Towne in a <hi>Diſguiſe,</hi> and betake himſelfe for <hi>ſecurity,</hi> to the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Armie about <hi>Newarke</hi> upon <hi>Trent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Scots,</hi> they entertained (I will not ſay they ſought it) as an happy <hi>Occaſion,</hi> to bring their owne <hi>Ends</hi> about with the <hi>Houſes;</hi> and knowing that the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> in their hands, was a <hi>Jewell</hi> that the two <hi>Houſes</hi> would purchaſe at any Price (they not thinking themſelves ſecure without ſuch a <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi>) it was not long ere they ſtrook a <hi>Bargain</hi> to deliver his <hi>Majeſty</hi> into the hands of <hi>Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> appointed by the <hi>Houſes</hi> to receive him; which was done accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly (<hi>Proh Deûm atque hominum fidem!</hi>) and the <hi>Scots</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved 200000 li. in part of their <hi>Arreares,</hi> and had a time ſet for tho paiment of the <hi>Reſidue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>Majeſty</hi> thus yeelded up (to ſay no worſe of it,) was conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> to reſide at <hi>Holdenby,</hi> during the will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116187:5"/>of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> faction; which then ruled the <hi>Roſte,</hi> and <hi>mued</hi> him up there many Monethes, in hope to tire him out of his <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Principles,</hi> and make him ſubmit to be yoked by the <hi>Propoſitions;</hi> yet all in vaine,</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Army</hi> under Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> quarteridg round about, and being moſt of them of a contrary <hi>Faction,</hi> and trampled upon by their <hi>Oppoſites,</hi> confederated with high <hi>Reſolution,</hi> to make that advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his <hi>Majeſties</hi> perſon which others had done before. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was an <hi>Attempt</hi> of an high <hi>Nature,</hi> which might ſeem upon a ſuddain to reflect upon the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Houſes,</hi> wherein their <hi>Adverſaries</hi> then bore ſway, the <hi>ſuperiour Officers</hi> agreed to carry it ſo cleanly, that they would not be ſeene at firſt to have any hand in the buſines, but it was left to a ſelect number of the <hi>private Souldiers,</hi> over whom a <hi>Coronet</hi> (by name <hi>Joyce</hi>) was ſet <hi>Commander in Chiefe,</hi> to ſeize upon the perſon of the <hi>King,</hi> and carry dim from <hi>Holdenby:</hi> which was done with expedition, and though the <hi>Superiour Officers</hi> diſclaimed the <hi>Act</hi> at firſt, yet they began to owne it by <hi>Degrees</hi> and carried him along with the <hi>Army</hi> from place to place, giving him and his <hi>party</hi> great hopes in their ſeverall <hi>Declarations,</hi> of their candid Intentions to reſtore him to hs juſt <hi>Rights,</hi> with <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Safety,</hi> and the <hi>Kingdom</hi> to a ſpeedy <hi>Peace;</hi> by which meanes they won the hearts of all, and rendred themſelves ſo <hi>formidable,</hi> that they beate downe the <hi>adverſe faction,</hi> over-awed and ſubdued the <hi>City,</hi> and brought the <hi>Houſes</hi> to act wholly for them and their <hi>Party.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At length, after his <hi>Majeſty</hi> had been ſettled ſome time under the power of the <hi>Army</hi> at <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> (where he ſtill continues) they having likewiſe been uſed to <hi>Rule,</hi> became loth to return to the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Obeying,</hi> &amp; forgetting the eſtabliſhment of his <hi>Majeſty</hi> (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to promiſe) thought of nothing, but which way to eſtabliſh <hi>Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> in a <hi>Military</hi> Poſture of 30000. for a perpetuall <hi>burthen</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and have left his <hi>Majeſty</hi> to be vexed again with <hi>Propoſitions</hi> from the <hi>Houſes,</hi> as unreaſonable as the former; yea worſe, inſomuch that the <hi>Independents little finger</hi> proves <hi>heavier then the</hi> Presbyters <hi>loynes:</hi> which gives us just occaſion to ſuſpect, that ſeeing now at the <hi>laſt caſt,</hi> they meane to make no end, and give us no hopes of a <hi>ſettled Peace,</hi> by tendring ſuch <hi>Propoſitions</hi> as his <hi>Majeſty</hi> may with <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and <hi>Honor</hi> accept, both they and the <hi>Houſes</hi> have ſome deſperate ends upon his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> as well as their brutiſh <hi>Adjutators,</hi> though at preſent they ſeeme to drive contrary waies.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116187:5"/>
            <p>For, what may we expect, when we ſee ſo little hope of an end? Hath not His <hi>Majeſty</hi> been a Priſoner a long ſeaſon? Is he not ſo ſtill? and what hope is there of his <hi>deliverance?</hi> let all <hi>Loyall-Subjects</hi> lay this to their heart. For the experience of former <hi>Ages</hi> and our owne <hi>Hiſtories</hi> will tell us, that a <hi>King</hi> long a <hi>Priſoner</hi> in his own Kingdome, is like <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the <hi>Grave,</hi> and can hardly expect a <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> but by miracle: For, his <hi>Adverſaries</hi> knowing the crime of <hi>Impriſoning</hi> to be unpardonable, will be tempted at laſt to ſome further miſchiefe for their own ſecurity, according to that of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca; Scelera ſceleribus propaganda,</hi> and that part of the <hi>Devils</hi> Lecture in <hi>Machiavell,</hi> that <hi>he which once drawes his Sword againſt his Prince, muſt throw away the Scabbard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I ſtated the whole progreſſe of affaires, according to <hi>Truth,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt His <hi>Majeſty</hi> and the two <hi>Houſes,</hi> wherein who ſees not how groſſely he hath been abuſed, both in the <hi>originall</hi> and continuance of this uncivill <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill-Warre,</hi> to the apparent hazard of <hi>Monarchy</hi> it ſelfe, the danger of His <hi>Royall Perſon,</hi> and the deſolation of His <hi>Kingdomes?</hi> what then remaines, but that the <hi>Houſes</hi> ſhould enter into a <hi>ſerious</hi> conſideration.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that though it being neither deſired nor expected, that they ſhould make an open <hi>Recantation</hi> of their former proceedings unto the world, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a rule among <hi>Stateſmen</hi> never to repent in the ſight of men, whatſoever they do before <hi>God,</hi> for feare of loſing their <hi>Reputation;</hi> yet it is wiſedome to retreat as ſpeedily, and with as little noiſe or reluctancie as may be, out of an <hi>erroneous Ingagement:</hi> Nor is it ſafe to <hi>dally</hi> with old out-worne <hi>Pretences</hi> any longer, now the people begin to be convinced daily, and in all <hi>Countries</hi> to ſee how ſtrangely they have been deluded: For, though the <hi>multitude</hi> are uſually as pliant as <hi>wax,</hi> and apt to be inamored of any <hi>Novelty</hi> that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes much to them of <hi>Eaſe, Liberty, Reformation,</hi> &amp;c. which are the moſt taking <hi>Pretences</hi> that can be made uſe of to inveigle them, and the onely <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements</hi> firſt practiſed by this <hi>Parliament</hi> to draw them on; yet when they finde their expectations defeated, and themſelves laden with <hi>oppreſſions</hi> worſe than the former;</p>
            <q>
               <l>—nec Bellua ſaevior ulla eſt,</l>
               <l>Quam ſervi rabies in libera colla furentis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Their <hi>Splenes</hi> are ready to burſt with <hi>Revenge;</hi> they carry all before them like a furious <hi>Inun lation,</hi> and uſually become the firſt <hi>Executioners</hi> of their friendly <hi>Pretenders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it is true that <hi>Hiſtories</hi> tell us, that <hi>Subjects</hi> have prevailed ſo farre as to <hi>depoſe,</hi> and execute direfull <hi>Tragedies</hi> upon their <hi>Soveraignes,</hi> and I could wiſh that our owne <hi>Iſland</hi> and the memories of ſome of our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters had never been ſtained with the guilt of ſo Prodigious a <hi>Crime;</hi> But then withall you ſhall finde, that thoſe executions were attempted only upon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116187:6"/>ſuch as were <hi>vicious</hi> in their lives, <hi>cruell</hi> and <hi>ſavage</hi> toward their <hi>Subjects,</hi> and <hi>incorrigible</hi> in their Government: <hi>But as for our gracious Soveraigne <hi>Charles,</hi> hath he not been of an <hi>unſpotted</hi> life? catechiſe your <hi>conſciences,</hi> and tel me what one habituall <hi>vice</hi> can he be taxed with? hath he not all his daies been a Patterne of admirable <hi>Clemency,</hi> even to his very <hi>Enemies?</hi> hath hee not obliged heretofore moſt of thoſe which have been the <hi>Ring-laeders</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, (thoſe Monſters</hi> of Ingratitude) with many ſpeciall benefits and favors? And touching his <hi>Government,</hi> if any thing were am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le (as all the <hi>falſe colours</hi> begin now to weare away) never did any of his <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> condeſcend ſo low, to give ſatisfaction to the people. By which <hi>gracious demeanour</hi> being highly mounted in the major part of his <hi>Subjects,</hi> it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible the <hi>malice</hi> of his <hi>Adverſaries</hi> ſhould extend to the ruine of his <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> or to the prejudice of the <hi>Regall Dignity,</hi> without ſome ſharp and ſwift Revenge upon the traiterous Abettors.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Houſes</hi> having rendred themſelves odious, both by their <hi>Ordinances</hi> and <hi>Agents,</hi> even among thoſe which have beene heretofore then <hi>faſt-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>runds,</hi> who finding nothing but oppreſſion upon oppreſſion, with daily <hi>Rapes</hi> committed upon their <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Perſons,</hi> as the onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence for all their <hi>Service</hi> which they have done them, and no likelihood as yet, that their <hi>miſeries</hi> will have an end, by reaſon of that ſtubburne di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which they keep ſtill, from all probability of an <hi>Accommodation</hi> with His <hi>Majeſty;</hi> the people begin now to looke upon him as one abuſed, and much to be pittied; they behold him as the onely <hi>Reſtorer</hi> of Liberty, and upon whoſe <hi>Reſtauration</hi> depends their owne (as indeed it doth) together with the <hi>Happineſſe, Peace</hi> and <hi>Tranquillity</hi> of the Kingdome: Is it not the <hi>common voice,</hi> wee ſhall never <hi>ſee a good world till the King bee in his Throne?</hi> What leſſe then can be expected by reaſonable men, but that the whole <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> (tired out with extremities) will ere long bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed into an unanimous deſigne upon the <hi>Houſes,</hi> as the <hi>Authours</hi> of all theſe <hi>diſt actions?</hi> And then as they ſet on <hi>Tumults</hi> from the <hi>City,</hi> to drive away His <hi>Majeſty</hi> from <hi>Weſtminster;</hi> ſo it's probable an <hi>univerſall Tumult</hi> may bring him back again, to be revenged upon his <hi>Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſeeing the <hi>Houſes</hi> have had now His <hi>Majeſty</hi> a long time in durance, (the higheſt and boldeſt <hi>Attempt</hi> which can bee made upon a <hi>Prince</hi> and the <hi>loweſt condition</hi> hee can be driven to; and which if it bee a <hi>Plag e</hi> to a <hi>private</hi> man, muſt needs bee an <hi>Hell</hi> to a <hi>King,</hi>) and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their <hi>Batteries</hi> by <hi>Perſwaſions</hi> and <hi>Frights,</hi> they have not been able to ſhake him from thoſe <hi>Royall Principles</hi> whereupon his <hi>Intereſt</hi> is firmly founded, and which are indeed his maine <hi>Security;</hi> To what end do they keep Him and his <hi>People</hi> any longer in <hi>Bondage,</hi> without all hope of <hi>Settlement?</hi> Let them conſider, that what they have done hitherto, they have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116187:6"/>attained by the love of that part of the <hi>People,</hi> upon whom they have had the luck to prevaile by their artificiall <hi>Pretences:</hi> But now that the <hi>Vizard</hi> is taken off, and every man is ſeen with his owne face; now the <hi>Curtain</hi> is withdrawne, and every man appears what he is in the cloſe of the <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy,</hi> and how he hath <hi>Acted</hi> all this while a <hi>knaviſh part</hi> under a religious <hi>diſguiſe,</hi> they muſt needs at length prove a <hi>ſhame</hi> to each other, and a <hi>ſcorne</hi> to their <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> when their <hi>Conſidents</hi> ſhall withdraw their <hi>Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and expoſe them to the <hi>malice</hi> of the <hi>oppreſſed</hi> and unruly <hi>multitude,</hi> or yeeld them up a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to the mercy of the <hi>Laws</hi> &amp; their <hi>injured Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, If all other wayes of <hi>ruine</hi> ſhould ſaile, yet being divided into <hi>Factions,</hi> there is a neceſſity they muſt at length become their owne <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners</hi> as they have been in part already, in that buſineſſe of Impeaching many of their <hi>Brethren in iniquity</hi> in both <hi>Houſes.</hi> In the proſecution whereof, though they coole at preſent (as it is wiſedome ſo to doe) and there be a kinde of friendly correſpond betwixt both the <hi>Factions;</hi> yet the friendſhip is but like that of two <hi>Maſtives</hi> tired with fighting, which ſtill and pant over each other, till the one can recover breath and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to fall againe upon the other. The reaſon why the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> doth not buſtle, is, becauſe as yet he cannot, and dares not, though his <hi>Appetite</hi> be keen enough; and the cauſe why the <hi>Independants</hi> are ſo moderate toward the <hi>Presbyter,</hi> is, becauſe the pride of that <hi>Faction</hi> being quelled, &amp; themſelves become the only men of power, they are contented to let the other live by them like <hi>Brethren</hi> (though no otherwiſe but as <hi>underlings</hi>) to ſerve their ends upon them; which condition they are glad to accept of, but not without much regreet and diſdaine againſt the <hi>Independent</hi> Conquerours: ſo that as by their mutuall <hi>Bickerings</hi> they have made each other contemptible, ſo this <hi>forced love</hi> and ſeeming <hi>unity</hi> muſt (upon every <hi>alteration</hi> of Affairs) break forth into ſuch <hi>flames</hi> of <hi>diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as will in ſhort time prepare them for <hi>final ru ne</hi> and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Since theſe things are ſo, we muſt neceſſarily conclude, that as it is contrary to <hi>Conſcience</hi> for the two Houſes not to contribute their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt indeavours to reſtore a firm and happy Peace, after ſuch a cruell War, to receive the ſpirits of their dejected <hi>Countrymen;</hi> ſo it is apparent to all the <hi>world,</hi> that there is no viſible way left to procure this <hi>Peace,</hi> but a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Accommodation with His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> by ſending to him ſuch Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as may agree with <hi>Right Reaſon, Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Honour:</hi> And if the <hi>Peace</hi> of their languiſhing bleeding <hi>Country</hi> be not a ſufficient <hi>Motive,</hi> yet let a tender regard be had to their owne ſecurity, in this their tottering condition. Retreat, Retreat <hi>Gentlemen</hi> with ſpeed; you have beene at your higheſt pitch long ſince, and now in the opinion of all wiſe men are <hi>declining;</hi> take heed of a <hi>fall;</hi> it will be the moſt dangerous, one next to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116187:7"/>that of the <hi>bottomeleſſe Pit:</hi> the eies of the Kingdome are upon His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> as the <hi>riſing ſun</hi> that muſt cleare up their clouded <hi>ſpirits,</hi> and diſpell all thoſe <hi>miſts</hi> that are about him, and upon your ſelves, as the only hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of his and their happines. While ye have time make uſe of it, for, <hi>the night is far ſpent, the day is at hand</hi> wherein <hi>God</hi> will judge with righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judgement. As yet ye may ſave your credits in part, if you pleaſe; as yet it is poſſible ye may recover your <hi>Friends</hi> and allay the <hi>ſplenes</hi> of your old Adverſaries; but remember my words, if ye ſin wilfully againſt all the obligations of <hi>Religion, Honour</hi> and <hi>Policy,</hi> a time is comming where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ye muſt repent, &amp; with ſorrow confeſſe, that you neglected thoſe things w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſo nearly concerns the happines of your ſelves, &amp; of theſe <hi>Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Caſe of the <hi>King</hi> in relation to the Army.</head>
            <p>Having made it manifeſt unto the world how His <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath beene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed from time to time by the two <hi>Houſes,</hi> we come now to conſider of his uſage ſince he hath been under the power and diſpoſition of the <hi>Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After that this <hi>Army</hi> under the command of Sir <hi>Tho. Fairfax</hi> had clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and wholly ſuppreſſed the <hi>royall party,</hi> having no enemy to incounter, and being the only <hi>forces</hi> conſiderable in the <hi>Kingdome</hi> for number and <hi>Reputation,</hi> and being elevated with the opinion of their own <hi>merits;</hi> and the <hi>Houſes</hi> committing that great over-ſight of not disband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>major</hi> part of them (which had been ſufficient to prevent thoſe <hi>Inconveniences</hi> which have ſince enſured,) theſe <hi>ſword men</hi> having little further uſe of <hi>military</hi> Counſels, began to reflect upon Affaires of <hi>State,</hi> and being for the moſt part of a <hi>Faction</hi> contrary to the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> which then ſwayed all in the <hi>Houſes,</hi> wherein likewiſe themſelves had their <hi>Partiſans,</hi> from whom they had <hi>intelligence</hi> of all Proceedings of the other <hi>Party,</hi> at length the <hi>factions</hi> grew jealous of each other. The <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> they had reaſon to diſlike, that men of opinions and <hi>Intereſts</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from themſelves, ſhould continue any longer in <hi>Armes,</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly drove on for a ſpeedy <hi>disbanding:</hi> And the <hi>Independant</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, interpreted this a <hi>deſigne</hi> on purpoſe to ruinate the <hi>Army</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Upon theſe grounds <hi>jealouſies</hi> and differences grew higher &amp; higher; the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> having the <hi>Votes</hi> in the <hi>Houſes</hi> on their ſide, and ſheltring themſelves under the <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Privilege</hi> of <hi>Parl.</hi> grew very confident and active toward a <hi>disbanding,</hi> while the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> valuing the <hi>ſword</hi> in their hands above the noiſe of an <hi>empty Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege,</hi> pitched upon very high reſolutions, and concluded of no leſſe than an <hi>Impeachment</hi> againſt <hi>eleven Grandees</hi> of their <hi>adverſe</hi> party in the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> as enemies to the <hi>Peace</hi> and welfare of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and carried it on with ſo high an hand, that at length they not only purged the <hi>Grandees</hi> out of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> but prevailed in a ſhort time to over-awe all their oppoſites, both in the <hi>Houſes</hi> and the <hi>City.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:116187:7"/>
            <p>But ſuch <hi>attempts</hi> as theſe being lofty and dangerous, and fatall ever to the undertakers, it not well founded; therfore the <hi>ſuperiour Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> before they had adventure, continued which way to make ſure of the <hi>Souldiers,</hi> that they might adhere to them couragiouſly, in ſo difficult and doubtfull an <hi>Enterprize;</hi> and they adjudged it a politique courſe to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect ſuch a new military <hi>Order</hi> of men, which were never heard of in any <hi>Army</hi> but this, and theſe they named <hi>Agitators,</hi> choſen moſt out of the <hi>private Souldiers,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Inferiour Officers,</hi> whoſe buſineſſe was to <hi>agitate</hi> in the behalfe of each reſpective <hi>Regiment, Troop</hi> or <hi>Company</hi> at the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> and there ro repreſent the <hi>grievances</hi> of their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive <hi>Regiments, Troops</hi> or <hi>Companies,</hi> with ſuch <hi>expedients</hi> as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived neceſſary for the removall of thoſe <hi>grievances,</hi> by which means the meaneſt <hi>Souldier</hi> being intereſted in the affaires of the <hi>Army,</hi> and having free acceſſe to the <hi>Councell of War,</hi> by their <hi>Agitators</hi> or <hi>Deputies</hi> in all caſes of <hi>diſcontent</hi> whatſoever, they became the more firmly obliged in the midſt of all <hi>extremities</hi> &amp; acted with the greater <hi>cheerfulnes</hi> &amp; <hi>unanimity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though this courſe was at firſt extreme beneficiall to the promo-thing of the <hi>deſigne</hi> then in hand, yet it was not long ere the <hi>Commanders in Chiefe</hi> had experience of thoſe manifold <hi>Inconveniences,</hi> which muſt neceſſarily follow, where <hi>private</hi> Perſons, and the <hi>Rabble</hi> of the vulgar are admitted to the cognizance of <hi>publick affaires:</hi> for by degrees they proceeded from <hi>private</hi> buſineſſes, to intermeddle (as the <hi>ſuperiour Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> taught them the way) not only with the maine Concernments of the <hi>Army</hi> in generall, but alſo with the grand <hi>Affairs</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> and Procced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Houſes;</hi> and at this day they are arrived to ſuch a height, that they are bold to ſtand in competition with the <hi>ſuperiour Officers</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: ſo that as the caſe now ſtands, we muſt conſider two <hi>diviſions</hi> of power in the <hi>Army,</hi> the <hi>ſuperiour Officers</hi> and the <hi>Agitators,</hi> and theſe to be diſtinct in their <hi>Motions,</hi> as it is pretended; for the <hi>ſuperiour Officers</hi> pretend to be for the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Agitators</hi> profeſſe down-right to bee neither for this <hi>King</hi> nor any other, but proclaime themſelves enemies to <hi>Monarchicall</hi> government, and the <hi>Queſtion</hi> now propounded at every <hi>Muſter,</hi> is, whether we ſhall have a <hi>King</hi> or <hi>no King?</hi> And in purſuance of their wicked <hi>Purpoſes,</hi> they are drawing up an <hi>impeachment</hi> againſt His Majeſty, which yet is publickly diſclaimed by ſome (but not all) of the <hi>ſuperiour Officers;</hi> but the maine <hi>Quere</hi> is, whether they are reall in it, or not; which I muſt conclude in the <hi>Negative</hi> for theſe following <hi>Reaſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, if they are reall againſt the deſigne of the <hi>Agitators,</hi> why then doe they not quicken the <hi>Houſes</hi> to ſome ſpeedy <hi>Agreement</hi> with His <hi>Majeſty,</hi> ſince there is no other probable way of quelling the extremity of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116187:8"/>ſuch deſperate <hi>Proceedings?</hi> for we perceive plainly, they runne on with the <hi>Houſes</hi> in the old deceitfull way of <hi>pretending</hi> toward <hi>Peace,</hi> by new <hi>Propoſitions</hi> caſt in the ſame <hi>mole</hi> with the former; which are indeed the ſame with, and in ſome <hi>Particulars</hi> worſe then the old, onely they ſhall viſit <hi>His Majeſty</hi> after a new way: for as they were preſented heretofore all in a <hi>Bundle,</hi> ſo now they meane to <hi>ſhufflle and out</hi> with them one by one; and then if His <hi>Majeſty</hi> refuſe to <hi>ſigne</hi> them (as their <hi>Conſciences</hi> tell them before hand, he will, muſt and ought,) then they and their <hi>Houſes</hi> have agreed, to ſettle the Affairs of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> without him, as ſhall ſeem beſt to their own <hi>Wiſedomes.</hi> And now ſince theſe men are no <hi>fooles,</hi> unleſſe it be in that higheſt point of <hi>folly</hi> (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeakes) to imagine <hi>there is no God,</hi> and ſo are not ignorant, that there is no way of <hi>ſecurity</hi> which <hi>loyall Subjects</hi> may expect, nor any way of <hi>ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement,</hi> but one, in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and that is by the <hi>royall Aſſent</hi> in all things to be eſtabliſhed; what then may we expect, if they ſettle things after their owne <hi>humour,</hi> and leave His <hi>Majeſty</hi> unſetled, but that they meane to ſhake the <hi>Crowne</hi> from off his <hi>Head,</hi> as well as the <hi>Agitators,</hi> the <hi>Devill</hi> prompting them thereunto upon a wicked <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>ſelfe-preſervation,</hi> to eſtabliſh their own <hi>ſafety</hi> againſt all <hi>after-claps</hi> of <hi>revenge,</hi> by a deſtruction of the <hi>Prince,</hi> and a depriving of his <hi>Poſterity,</hi> by an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Though this ſeeme to be a moſt prodigious Courſe, and ſuch a one as honeſt moderate men ſcarce dreame of, eſpecially at this time now that the <hi>Councell of Warre</hi> pretends againſt the <hi>Agitators,</hi> yet if wee reflect upon the Principles of their <hi>leading men,</hi> wee can expect no leſſe, as long as they keep at ſuch a diſtance from his <hi>Majestie.</hi> For, they have <hi>Martin</hi> a <hi>Demi-god</hi> amongſt them, who preached this <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> long ſince in the <hi>Houſe</hi> againſt the <hi>King,</hi> that <hi>it were better one Man and his Poſteritie ſhould periſh</hi> ROOT <hi>and</hi> BRANCH, <hi>than the Kingdome,</hi> that is, than Themſelves and their <hi>Faction</hi> ſhould miſcarry. And Major <hi>White</hi> (he that profeſſed openly He knew <hi>no Authoritie in the Kingdome, but the power of the Sword,</hi>) He is a man that <hi>plants</hi> and <hi>waters</hi> the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> with the ſame Principles as <hi>Martin,</hi> and proclaimed the very ſame <hi>doctrine</hi> in the Head of the <hi>Generalls</hi> owne <hi>Regiment,</hi> at their laſt <hi>Muſter</hi> in <hi>Hartfordſhire.</hi> And if wee conſider M. <hi>Cromwell's</hi> old <hi>Tenets,</hi> he is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a jot behind in <hi>madneſſe,</hi> notwithſtanding all his <hi>Smooth Tricks</hi> at preſent. Nor will <hi>Ireton's</hi> whining <hi>Plea</hi> for the <hi>King,</hi> with all the <hi>Noiſe</hi> he made lately againſt the <hi>Agitators,</hi> passe for any other but meere <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowy Pretences,</hi> unleſſe wee receive ſome viſible hopes of a <hi>Subſtantiall Accord betwixt</hi> them and his <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> by a moderate and ſpeedy <hi>Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention;</hi> elſe wee muſt conclude, that the late <hi>Carriages</hi> were but ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116187:8"/>ſubtile <hi>Policies</hi> to make a faire ſhew to the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> till their <hi>deſign</hi> ſhould be fully ripened, and then when they had a ſit <hi>Oportunitie,</hi> to have Cloſed with their <hi>Agitators.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It muſt be very probable, that They and their <hi>Agitators</hi> are one in <hi>deſigne,</hi> becauſe They, the <hi>Houſes,</hi> and the <hi>Agitators,</hi> appeare one in reſolution: For, as the <hi>Houſes</hi> and <hi>Themſelves</hi> have agreed already, that upon his <hi>Majeſties</hi> refuſall of their <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> they will diſpoſe of <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires</hi> at then own pleaſure; So the <hi>Agitators</hi> have told us in Print plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that They are <hi>reſolved not to depend for the Settlement of their Peace and Freedome, upon the King, who</hi> (they ſay) <hi>intended their Bondage, and brought a cruell Warre upon Them;</hi> and atheiſme, that as <hi>it is the higheſt disparagement to the Supreme Authoritie of this Nation, the Parliament, that when they have Commanded an Army in Service againſt the King they ſhould not have ſufficient power to ſave them harmeleſſe for obedience to their Commands; ſo as the Higheſt diſhonour to the Army, that they ſhould ſeeke to the conquered Enemy to ſave them harmeleſſe for fighting againſt Them, which is to aske him pardon, and ſo will remaine as a perpetuall Reproach up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</hi> And now what difference (I pray you) betwixt the Sence of the <hi>Houſes,</hi> the <hi>ſuperior Officers,</hi> and their <hi>Agitators?</hi> Are they not all one? They were all agreed in <hi>private</hi> to ruine his <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> and the <hi>Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> were to act it firſt in <hi>publique:</hi> From whence it is as cleare as the <hi>Sun</hi> that ſhines at noon day, that as their firſt <hi>Pretences</hi> when they got the <hi>King</hi> into their poſſeſſion, were all for the good of his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which wee have found by experience to be but fained and falſe; So their laſt Actions are like to manifeſt that their chiefeſt Aime was, and is no other, but to deprive the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Poſteritie</hi> of th ir <hi>juſt Rights,</hi> and our <hi>Nation</hi> of that honourable name and conſtitution of a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> whereby it hath flouriſhed many hundreds of yeares, even to the admiration and envy of all the Kingdomes in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this may be fully layd open to all men, let us next of all conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how farre the <hi>Agitators</hi> have driven on the <hi>deſign</hi> and in what <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</hi> And herein I ſhall faithfully quote them and their <hi>Abettors,</hi> in all their <hi>Repreſentations</hi> and <hi>Propoſalls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, They reſolve in the <hi>Caſe of the Army ſtated,</hi> &amp;c <hi>pag.</hi> 6. to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the <hi>Negative voice</hi> of the King, eſteeming it unreaſonable, that they having purchaſed by <hi>blood</hi> what was their <hi>Right,</hi> of which the <hi>King</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to deprive them, ſhould yet ſolely depend on his will, for their reliefe in their <hi>grievances</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſions;</hi> and that ſatisfaction and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is to be given to the people in relation th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> for which they expended ſo much <hi>treaſure</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> before the <hi>King</hi> ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:116187:9"/>
            <p>Secondly, They have declared <hi>pag.</hi> 15. That all power is <hi>originally</hi> and <hi>eſſentially</hi> in the whole body of the People of this Nation, and their free choice or Conſent by their <hi>Repreſentators,</hi> is the only <hi>Originall</hi> or founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all juſt government, and therefore that it be inſiſted upon poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; That the Supreme power of the Peoples <hi>Repreſentors,</hi> or <hi>Commons</hi> Aſſembled in <hi>Parliament,</hi> be forthwith clearely declared; as their power to make <hi>Lawes,</hi> or repeale <hi>Lawes,</hi> as alſo to call to an Account all <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> in this <hi>Nation</hi> whatſoever, for their Neglects or Treacheries in their <hi>Trusts</hi> for the <hi>Peoples</hi> good, and to continue, or to diſplace and remove them from their Offices, Dignities, and <hi>Truſts,</hi> according to their <hi>deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</hi> And farther, that a Power to conſtitute any kind of Governours, or <hi>Officers,</hi> that they ſhall judge to be for the peoples good, be declared: And that upon the aforeſaid conſiderations it be inſiſted upon, that all Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to the freedome and equalitie of the peoples choice of thoſe their <hi>Repreſentors,</hi> eitheir by <hi>Patents</hi> or <hi>Charters,</hi> or <hi>Uſurpations,</hi> or <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Cuſtomes,</hi> be removed by theſe preſent Commons in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and that ſuch a freedome of Choice be provided for, as the People may be equally <hi>Repreſented:</hi> Which power or <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> is the thing againſt which (they ſay) the <hi>King</hi> hath conſented, and the <hi>People</hi> have defended with their lives, and therefore ought now to be demanded, as the <hi>price of their blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>pag.</hi> 17. That all thoſe large Summes of money that were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to needleſſe pretended <hi>Officers of the Court,</hi> which did but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe wickedneſſe and prophaneneſſe, may be reſerved for a <hi>publique Treaſure,</hi> to be expended in paying thoſe <hi>Forces</hi> that muſt be maintained for the Peoples Safetie, that ſo through a good and faithfull Improvement of all the <hi>Lands</hi> pertaining to the Court, there might be much reſerved for levying; the <hi>publique Charges,</hi> and caſing the people.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, That the power of this, and all future <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> is inferior onely to theirs who chuſe them, and doth extend with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the concurrence or conſent of any other Perſon or Perſons, to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting, altering, and repealing of <hi>Lawes;</hi> to the erecting and aboliſhing of <hi>Offices</hi> and <hi>Courts;</hi> to the appoynting, removing, and calling to an Accompt <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> of all Degrees; to the making <hi>Warre</hi> and <hi>Peace;</hi> to the <hi>Treating</hi> with <hi>Foraine States:</hi> And generally to what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not expreſſely, or implyed, reſerved by the <hi>Repreſented</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, That in all <hi>Lawes</hi> made, or to be made, every Perſon may be bound alike, and that no <hi>Tenure, Eſtate, Charter, Degree, Birth,</hi> or <hi>Place,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:116187:9"/>doe conferre any exemption from the ordinary courſe of <hi>legall proceedings,</hi> whereunto others are ſubjected.</p>
            <p>And now let all the world judge from theſe particulars, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>deſign</hi> be not point blank againſt <hi>Kingly Government,</hi> when the <hi>King</hi> (whom by their known <hi>Principles</hi> they reckon for no more but an <hi>Officer of State</hi>) ſhal be deveſted of his <hi>Negative voyce,</hi> and of all <hi>power</hi> and <hi>priviledge,</hi> and ſtand liable to <hi>criminall</hi> Accuſations, &amp; be utterly deptived of his <hi>Nobility,</hi> which are the main props of his <hi>Prerogative</hi> &amp; <hi>Crown.</hi> This is plainly evident to any common underſtanding that weighs the foregoing <hi>demands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in that deſperate <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> entituled <hi>A Call to the Army &amp;c.</hi> the language is farre more plaine, where they tell us, that they are not to be frighted by the word ANARCHY, unto a love of MONARCHY, which is but the gilded name for <hi>Tyranny;</hi> proclaiming his Sacred <hi>Majesty</hi> the verieſt <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> living in the word, <hi>pag.</hi> 1. taxing the <hi>Houſes,</hi> that they did not puniſh him in the firſt place, as the <hi>chiefe Author of all our miſeries,</hi> and an abuſer of his <hi>Office,</hi> and a man <hi>over-head and eares in bloud, pag.</hi> 5. and preſſing to diſpatch their <hi>Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> againſt him: And to ſum up all their villany, they conclude in theſe very words, that thoſe of their friends that are about him, ſhould not permit any <hi>Agreement</hi> to be made with him, but <hi>be ſure to keep him, as they keep their lives, and not to part with him upon any terms till they can referre him to a free Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that now their <hi>Deſigne</hi> appeares with a broad face in the world, that they were reſolved not to come to any Agreemet, or Accommondation with his Majeſty, but to have mued him up till the time ſhould come, wherein they had determined this Parliament ſhould expire, and then to have deſtroyed him in a New Parliament (forſooth) or rather a Tumultuous Aſſembly of their own framing.</p>
            <p>Nor doe they ſteep in this curſed buſineſſe, but have <hi>Agents</hi> of their own in all Quarters of the <hi>Army,</hi> the <hi>Countries</hi> abroad, and the City of <hi>London,</hi> to draw in <hi>Perſons</hi> to ſubſcribe to the afornamed damned <hi>particulars.</hi> And it hath been my good hap to light upon a Copy of <hi>Inſtructions</hi> agreed upon by the <hi>Agents</hi> of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the <hi>Army,</hi> to the reſpective <hi>Counties, Cities,</hi> and <hi>Pariſhes,</hi> whereunto ſeverall <hi>Papers</hi> of thoſe <hi>particulars</hi> were directed by the chiefe <hi>Conspirators,</hi> for the more orderly carrying on, and the more ſpeedy effecting
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116187:10"/>and bringing in the <hi>ſubſcriptions.</hi> The <hi>Inſtructions</hi> are theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the <hi>Papers</hi> be delivered to ſuch faithfull perſons, as will be vigilant, and active in proſecution of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly. That they be deſired to meet at places which they ſhall judge moſt convenient, to take the <hi>Subſcriptions</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> or place where they reſide.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that there be appointed one or more <hi>Agents,</hi> as they ſhall judge meet, to bring in the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubſcriptions</hi> as ſoone as poſſibly they can, to the <hi>Saracen's Head</hi> in <hi>Friday-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> where there will be <hi>Agents</hi> to receive them, or the <hi>Maſter</hi> of the Houſe (let that <hi>fellow</hi> be taken notice of) will direct them where they ſhall be received.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that one or more active faithfull man be appointed for each <hi>County, City,</hi> or <hi>Place,</hi> as aforeſaid, to act and tranſact ſuch things as may conduce to the good of the <hi>work</hi> in hand.</p>
            <p>By all which it appeares, that the <hi>Caſe</hi> of the King in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the <hi>Army,</hi> was a very ſad one, and ſuch as repreſents him in a moſt deſperate condition, while he reſided among them; eſpecially, if we conſider that part of his <hi>Majeſtie</hi>'s Letter directed to the <hi>Houſes,</hi> and left behind him in his Chamber, at his departure from <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes all that is before ſpecified, and wherein he lets the <hi>Houſes</hi> know, That he had as much as in him lay, endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to give them ſatisfaction, and to re-eſtabliſh a <hi>ſetled peace;</hi> but he ſaw nothing reaſonable would content them; That he had certain Information that the <hi>Agitators,</hi> or ſome of that <hi>Faction,</hi> had an Intent to murther him; and that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Peters</hi> had lately expreſſed ſo much to an <hi>intimate friend</hi> of his, for which Cauſe he was reſolved to retire to ſome <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> place for a Time, for his own <hi>Preſervation</hi> &amp;c. as it was high time ſo doe, when the long plotted <hi>villany</hi> was come ſo neare an <hi>execution.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Caſe of the King in relation to the Scots.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as it is very convenient to bury all the paſt <hi>Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> done to his <hi>Majesty,</hi> by his own <hi>Nation,</hi> they having afforded us ſo great hope in their late <hi>Addreſſe</hi> unto the <hi>Houſe,</hi> that they meane to redeeme the Time and recover their <hi>credit,</hi> by a ſolemn profeſſion and vindication of their <hi>Loyalty;</hi> I ſhall forbeare to rub <hi>old ſoares,</hi> or mention that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116187:10"/>
               <hi>ſtrange Act,</hi> in yeelding up the <hi>King</hi> to the power of the <hi>Houſes,</hi> his profeſſed <hi>Enemies;</hi> which themſelves at the firſt poſitively denyed to do in their Anſwer to the Papers of the <hi>Houſes;</hi> and condemned it, as a thing unheard of, and not to be in reaſon expected, it being contrary to the Law of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> that they ſhould yeeld up their own <hi>Prince,</hi> ſled unto them for <hi>Reſuge</hi> to the power of another <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though by forfeiting this Principle of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>honour,</hi> they have contracted a grand <hi>Odium</hi> in the opinion of the <hi>Royall Party</hi> at home, and other <hi>Nations</hi> abroad (as they well know,) inſomuch that men will hardly be perſwaded they intend any good toward his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty;</hi> yet their own <hi>intereſts</hi> and <hi>ends</hi> being bound up in it (as I ſhall evidently demonſtrate, and beyond which the <hi>jealouſie</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation can build no <hi>conſidence</hi> upon them) I ſhall evince it to every mans underſtanding (and to quicken the <hi>Scots</hi> themſelves) that as his <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath no hope as yet of a recovery, but by their meanes; ſo in all reaſons a neceſſity lies upon them, the State of their own Affaires <hi>requiring</hi> them to aſſiſt, and reſtore his <hi>Majeſty:</hi> which will appear more clearly by theſe following <hi>Reaſons:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, a principall end in all the <hi>Actions</hi> of this <hi>Army,</hi> and their <hi>partakers</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> hath been utterly to baniſh all <hi>Scotch</hi> Intereſt our of <hi>England;</hi> which they have in a manner wholly <hi>effected,</hi> by cruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Grandees</hi> of the <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Faction; only to <hi>ſtill</hi> and <hi>pacifie</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> at preſent, they have permitted the reſidue to ſit ſtill in the <hi>Houſe</hi> to ſerve their own ends upon them; and ſo likewiſe the <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian</hi> Church-Government is on foot too, but only upon <hi>courteſie</hi> for a time, to ſeed them with hopes, and keep them from running upon <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams,</hi> while in the meane time the <hi>Independents</hi> are plotting to make ſure work, and then when they ſee convenient, to kick off, both them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> paſt all hope of a recovery; and when they have prevailed ſo farce as to ſhut the <hi>Scots</hi> out of doores to <hi>bolt</hi> them faſt after them, and not leave the leaſt hope of a <hi>Re-entry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It cannot ſtand with the honour of the <hi>Scots</hi> to have their whole <hi>Nation</hi> baſſted by an inconſiderable <hi>Party</hi> in this: And by the ordinary rules of <hi>Policy,</hi> every Faction is obliged to quell its <hi>Oppoſite,</hi> or loſe that <hi>Intereſt</hi> which is contended for betwixt them. And therefore if the <hi>Scots</hi> ſit ſtill, and break not the <hi>Cariere</hi> of this <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> Party, by a timely <hi>Interpoſition</hi> but let them ſettle upon the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> what can they expect, but that when all is ſubdued to their will here, their next Deſign will he upon them in their own <hi>Kingdome?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116187:11"/>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Scots</hi> have often declared heretofore, that the happineſſe of both <hi>Kingdomes</hi> were mutually involved ſo as that nothing of preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice could befall the one, but it muſt reflect upon the other: And in their Papers from <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> preſented to both <hi>Houſes</hi> when his <hi>Majeſty</hi> was among them, and in their late <hi>Letter</hi> directed to the <hi>Houſe</hi> they having publikly declared (how unhappily ſoever they departed from that <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple</hi> heretofore) that their ſafety and happineſſe was included in that of his <hi>Majeſtie's</hi> perſon, it is impoſſible they ſhould make ſo ſlight of their <hi>Faith,</hi> as to ſacrifice it with <hi>eternall Infamy,</hi> and hazard themſelves and their liberty to ſerve their enemies, for the love of thoſe <hi>Arreares</hi> which are yet behind.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they may receive thoſe <hi>Arreares</hi> as eaſily and with more honour, from the hands of his <hi>Majesty,</hi> and with the conſent and love of the whole <hi>Kingdome,</hi> when they have reſtored his <hi>Majesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, their <hi>Party</hi> being wholly broken here, and the <hi>Houſes</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe themſelves, there is no hope of ſerving their <hi>ends</hi> any longer in a <hi>Parliamentary</hi> way; but upon the <hi>King</hi> they may, and ſerve him too: So that they have no way left to procute an <hi>Intereſt</hi> again to any purpoſe in this Nation but by cloſing with the King.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, notwithſtanding their former <hi>Parliamentary</hi> engagements, they are not to ſeek of a cleanly pretence to ſtand for his <hi>Majesty,</hi> as long as the <hi>Covenant</hi> is in being, and the <hi>Houſes</hi> and <hi>Army</hi> have broken that <hi>Covenant,</hi> by their palpable endeavours not only to ruine his <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie</hi>'s Perſon, but alſo to root out the very Principles of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> both which both They and the <hi>Houſes</hi> have <hi>Covenanted</hi> to defend.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, there can be no doubt of carrying the work through, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>miſcarriages</hi> of the Houſes, and the Affronts of the <hi>Army,</hi> have wholy made ſhip wrack of the Affections of the <hi>City;</hi> &amp; as for the reſt of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> variety of oppreſſions hath made them abſolutely the <hi>Kings</hi> own, reckoning their own deliverance to depend on his <hi>Roſtauration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, though it may be objected, there is a great diſtance betwixt the <hi>Scots</hi> and the <hi>Royall Party,</hi> in matter of <hi>Church-Government,</hi> and ſo little hope of a cordiall uniting betwixt them; yet I am bold to imagine, that ſince all the world knowes the Deſign of a <hi>Preſbytery</hi> by them upon this <hi>Nations,</hi> was only to quell their Adverſaries, the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> that were the only men which vexed them, and hindered them from thriving ſo well as they deſired in this Kingdom, and ſo to make a ſure footing here by trampling them under; it will be no hard matter to reconcile them ſo far, as to let us have <hi>Biſhops</hi> again, upon condition they may eſtabliſh themſelves here with them. And it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, they will be contented to ſave their own <hi>ſouls</hi> in their <hi>Kirk</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and let us alone with ours, if their <hi>Bodies</hi> and <hi>Purſes</hi> be well provided for in the Common-Wealth of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116187:11"/>
            <head>The Caſe of the <hi>King</hi> in relation to all his Loyall Subjects.</head>
            <p>VVHat the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have often boaſted of themſelves, as the only Nation under Heaven moſt zealous of the Honour of their Princes, might with as much truth and more modeſty, have bin verified in former times upon the Engliſh Nation, it having bin an old received Maxime of State amongſt them, That the glory of the Kingdom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, much in the State and Majeſtick ſplendour of their King.</p>
            <p>And God be bleſſed this <hi>Loyall principle</hi> is not yet worne out, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be in the <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>pract ſes</hi> of ſome few in theſe later yeares, who have <hi>ſold themſelves to work wickedneſſe,</hi> and been <hi>Ring-leaders in an open and moſt horrid Rebellion,</hi> wherein they had drawn in a great part of their <hi>fellow Subjects,</hi> to ſerve their own <hi>factions</hi> and <hi>ambitions</hi> ends, as hath been manifeſted ſufficiently in ſtating the ſeverall paſſages betwixt his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> the two <hi>Houſes,</hi> and the <hi>Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it remains in the next place to ſhew how the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the reſt of the Kingdome, hath been abuſed likewiſe, as well as the <hi>King,</hi> and what obligation lies upon them all, for the immediate en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring upon ſome Courſe for the Reſtauration of the <hi>King,</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of the Kingdome from the ſlavery and oppreſſion of a tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Parliament, and a more tyrannicall and inſulting Souldiery.</p>
            <p>No way more ready to finde out how the City and Kingdome have been abuſed, than by recounting the innumerable <hi>Tricks</hi> that have bin uſed to milk the <hi>Purſes</hi> of the people, in pretence of maintayning the Warre, when the leaſt part (God knowes) hath been imployed that that way, but either treaſured up in the purſes of the <hi>Members,</hi> or laid out by them in rich and fair purchaſes at home, or tranſported to ſerve their turnes abroad, againſt a <hi>rainy day,</hi> while the <hi>Souldiers</hi> have pined for want of pay in their <hi>religious cauſe,</hi> and devoured the poore <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen</hi> by <hi>Free quarter:</hi> For, whereas one or two wayes well ordered, would have ſerved the turne, they have made uſe of ſo various wayes, for raiſing of vaſt and incredible Summes of money, as were never heard of before at a time in one kingdome; whereof I will here ſet down the <hi>Catalogue.</hi> 1 Royall Subſidy of 300000 l. 2 Pole-money. 3 The Free Loanes and Contributions upon the Publique Faith, amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to avaſt incredible ſumme, in Money, Plate, Horſe, and Arms, Bod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, Thimbles, and Wedding-Rings of the zealous Siſters. 4 The Iriſh Adventure for ſale of Lands a firſt and ſecond time. 5 The week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meale. 6 The City-loane after the rate of fifty Subſidies. 7 The
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116187:12"/>Aſſeſments for bringing in the <hi>Scots.</hi> 8 The fifth and twentieth part. 9 The weekly Aſſeſment for the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his Army. 10 The weekly (or monthly) Aſſeſment for Sir <hi>Tho. Fairfax</hi> his Army. 11 The weekly Aſſeſment for the Scotiſh Army. 12 The weekly Aſſeſment for the Britiſh Army in <hi>Ireland.</hi> 13 The weekly Aſſeſment for my Lord of <hi>Mancheſters</hi> Army. 14 Free-Quarter (at leaſt) connived at by the State, becauſe the Souldiers having for a time ſubſiſtence that way, were the leſſe craving for pay; whereby their Arrears growing ſtale, muſt at laſt either be fruſtrated by a tedious <hi>Committee</hi> of <hi>Accounts,</hi> diſcount it out of the Commanders Arrears, whereby the State ſaves it. 15 The Kings Revenue. 16 Sequeſtrations and Plunder by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees, which if well anſwered to the State, would have carried on the work; which may be thus demonſtrated: One halfe of all the goods and chatrels, and (at leaſt) one halfe of all the Lands, Rents, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of the kingdome have bin Sequeſtred And who can imagine that one halfe of the profits and goods of the Land, will not maintayn any Forces that can be kept and fed in <hi>England,</hi> for the defence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? 17 Exciſe upon all things; this alone, if well managed, would have maintayned the warre: The <hi>Low-Countreys</hi> make it almoſt their only ſupport. 18 Fortification money All which amounting to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout forty <hi>Millions,</hi> have bin expended heretofore; whereto wee may adde ſince, the ſale of a great part of Biſhops Lands, which the unmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable ſummes ariſing ſtill by Fines for Delinquents Compoſitions, with the continuance of the Exciſe; and yet not ſo much as a penny disburſed for the pay of the ſouldiers, inſomuch that they threaten every moment to come and levy their Arreares within the City of <hi>London,</hi> which is become now the common mark of all intolerable <hi>affronts</hi> and <hi>injuries</hi> that the ingratitude of the Houſes, or the inſolent threats of the Souldiers can caſt upon them. And the Countrey groanes still under thoſe three heavy burthens, <hi>Exciſe, Taxes,</hi> and <hi>Free-Quarter,</hi> without hope when, or how they ſhall have remedy: But rather on the other ſide they ſee nothing but a cloud of perpetuall miſery and ſlavery hanging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their heads, ready to fall upon them by the late Votes of the Houſes and the generall Councell of the Army, for the eſtabliſhment of thirty thouſand ſtanding Forces in the Kingdom, with conſtant pay to be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied (for ought we know) if they once ſettle, to more then the third ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</p>
            <p>Then ſeeing theſe things are ſo (my dear Countrey men) it is very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident how the Caſe ſtands betwixt his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and you. Is not his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116187:12"/>Caſe your own? have ye not been alike abuſed, gulled, and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? Is not he deprived of his <hi>Crown,</hi> as you are of your Liberties and Eſtates? Is it not plaine that his <hi>Prerogative</hi> and your <hi>Freedome</hi> muſt fall together? And is not a ſpeedy ſettlement the only meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them? And is there my probability of ſetling, till his <hi>Majeſty</hi> be ſeated in his Throne? And hath it not been evidenced unto you, that there is no way to effect this, unleſſe the <hi>Houſes</hi> condeſcend to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation with his <hi>Majeſty?</hi> And this they will never do, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe all the Loyall hearts of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> do give them to underſtand by way of Declaration, or Petition, that they are very ſenſible of their own and his <hi>Majeſtyes</hi> diſtreſſed condition, and are reſolved with theit utmoſt poſſibilities (all as one man) to reſtore his <hi>Majeſty</hi> to his regal dignity, as the only meanes to procure eaſe and tranquility, to theſe wearied and diſtracted <hi>Kingdoms;</hi> toward which I commend unto them theſe few conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſeeing the <hi>Houſes</hi> and the <hi>Army</hi> ſtand wholly ingaged againſt the <hi>King,</hi> (as I have proved notwithſtanding all fair pretences,) and ſeeing they are both reſolute and active, and have the power of the Sword in their hands, there is a neceſſity, unleſſe we intend to have our miſeries intailed upon our poſterity, that all delayes be laid aſide, and ſome ſpeedy courſe taken to ballance their power, before they have ſtrengthen'd their party too much, and quite over-run the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and made ſure of all both by Sea and Land, at they have well nigh done already.</p>
            <p>Secondly, though the <hi>Army</hi> are a conſiderable Body for number, and ſo the very appearance of it might deterre men from ſtirring, yet if we conſider its conſtitution, either in whole, or in the parts of it, we ſhall finde it to be an Aggregate of differing Intereſts, opinions, and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; and ſince they agree in nothing, but to ruine us, ſo if any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance ſhould be made againſt them, or any vigorous ingagement be ſet on foot in the behalfe of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> ſo as that they be reduced to the leaſt plunge of hardſhip and difficulty, they would all moulder away to nothing: for, a great part (I dare ſay moſt) of the private Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are ſuch as have done, and would do his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſervice, if occaſion were offered; whereas they have betaken themſelves to that <hi>Army,</hi> and continue there, not out of any devotion or affection to their <hi>Cauſe,</hi> but only as Souldiers of Fortune, that have no where elſe at preſent to ſubſiſt, and ſo are willing upon any termes to imbrace eaſe and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance upon <hi>Free-quarter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Houſes</hi> and <hi>Army</hi> have quite loſt the affections of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116187:13"/>City of <hi>London,</hi> the only conſiderable party in this <hi>Kingdom</hi> to uphold a <hi>Deſign,</hi> and ſo of courſe now, ſeeing they can ſettle no where elſe, nor otherwiſe ſecure themſelves and their eſtates, they muſt return unto his <hi>Majeſty.</hi> And beſides, they openly profeſſe, they would with all their hearts ſpend as much more as they have done to reſtore his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and be revenged upon their <hi>Riders:</hi> So that if they be wrought upon by apt Inſtruments, againſt a right nick of time, they are ready to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine any courſe that carries a probability in the face of it, to redeeme their loſt liberties and reputation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, as the whole <hi>Kingdom</hi> is diſ-obliged by the <hi>Houſes</hi> and the <hi>Army,</hi> inſomuch that their own friends (eſpecially of the <hi>Presbyterian faction</hi>) are become as abſolute enemies to them as the <hi>Cavaliers;</hi> So the <hi>Scots</hi> being reputed the leading men of that party, and having decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in their late Letter to the <hi>Houſe,</hi> their diſlike of the Kings being in the power of the <hi>Army,</hi> and of their intended dealing towards him; And withall, that the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> doth reckon their ſtability and happineſſe, to depend upon the ſafety and preſervation of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> royall perſon, and are reſolved that no alteration of affaires, ſhall ever ſeperate them from the duty and allegiance they owe unto his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> nor from their conſtant reſolution to live in all Loyalty un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Government, then if they proceed really in this way they have begun, it will bring in all the <hi>Covenanters</hi> of both <hi>Kingdoms</hi> to the <hi>roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Party,</hi> and make their fingers itch to be in action againſt the <hi>adverſe</hi> Party, now predominant in the <hi>Houſes</hi> and <hi>Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſince God hath been pleaſed ſo to provide for the good of theſe <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and the ſafety of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> that he hath thus cleanly eſcaped their hands, and thereby the <hi>Army</hi> hath loſt their maine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in the poſſeſſion of his Perſon, and that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe, and hath freedom to ſhew himſelfe in the head of any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty when a happy opportunity ſhall be offered; Then if the <hi>Houſes</hi> and <hi>Army</hi> ſhall perſiſt ſtill in their horrible extremities, without all hope of a reaſonable accommodation, it is the duty of all men whoſe conſciences are touched but with a ſpark of honeſty, to aſſiſt him with their utmoſt endevours, againſt the rigorous demands and dealings of unreaſonable and cruell men, enemies to him as he is a <hi>King,</hi> enemies likewiſe to the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and profeſſed enemies to all regular Forms of Government; From whom good Lord deliver him, and ſet an end to his affliction.</p>
            <closer>Vive le ROY.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
